welcome this is our second question and
answer session and I appreciate all of
the enthusiasm first of all like again I
want to say thank you to my viewers the
amount of feedback it's been and support
has been really really wonderful and
I've also been impressed by the
enthusiasm for this Q&A session I want
to start by addressing a couple of big
questions that have surfaced through the
video series especially some of the last
episodes that have been posted and
they're sort of central and then after
that I'll address some questions that
have been tweeted and then at the end
we'll try and get into some live
questions so the one thing I want to
start with is this issue around
personhood because there has been some
discussion about like what am I saying
about personhood and what was I saying
about the newborn and I want to try and
go over this really really carefully
about the ontology personhood so I was
arguing that agape was necessary or at
least indispensable to the formation of
personhood and then some people are
asking questions about what did that
mean about what I thought about the
ontology of a newborn etc so let me be
very clear that I think a newborn has
the real potential for personhood and if
you note I made explicit attempt to
argue in the episode on Aristotle I
believe it's episode 6 that possibility
and potentiality are real they are a
definite part of the ontology and I
think that saying that a newborn has the
real potential is exactly what commits
us to our moral responsibilities to them
so to use a term that poetically uses I
think newborns have a a moral status as
persons precisely because that real
potential to be actualized as a person
it can only be actualized by the
informing of agape love and so we have a
moral obligation to bring about the
actualization of that real potential
through a gothic love and we do that
because of course persons are
intrinsically valuable to us now that
being said we should not confuse
potentiality and actuality to say that a
newborn is potentially a person and here
I'm speaking very technically and very
accurately is to say that it is not
actually a person because that's the
difference between actuality and
potentiality it needs agape to become an
actual person as opposed to being a
really potential person and that matters
because we value actuality different
than we value potentiality you would
rather have actual money than potential
money this has even been shown
experimentally you will take a little
bit of actual money now over you know
the real potential for money in the
future so the valuation and the
metaphysical status are importantly
different and notice that when you ask
okay well what make something actually
actually a person you're talking about
well what makes what is it to act as a
person and notice that we don't treat
infants as beings that can act as
persons they're not allowed to own
property they're not allowed to get
married they do not have freedom of
religion they cannot go where they
choose right they and also they cannot
commit a crime they are in no way moral
agents in an important sense we do not
treat them that way that does not mean
that we do not have an agape and moral
responsibility to them of course we do
and that's has what I have just argued
and then the thing - the thing to then
ask is well what is it to act as a
person and then to use a contrast that
many people use that love you know you
can love a dogged optically and it will
never become a person I agree and what
is it that a dog will never have what in
what way will the dog not be able to act
as a person certainly dogs have
conscious
certainly they have intelligence
certainly they have emotion certainly
they are able to enter to enter into
long term social relationships that's
exactly why we have dogs in our houses
and we treat them as members of our
family right but what is it a dog will
never have well the dog will never have
moral agency it will never have
reflective rationality it will never
have the capacity for self selphie
antral self transcendence and that's
exactly what is still missing in the
newborn the newborn cannot act in any of
those passions so when I said that a
newborn in that sense is not actually a
person but that is what I met and that
again is not lessening our moral
responsibility towards the newborn it is
increasing it because as I've just said
the newborn has the real potential to be
a person and that thereby really
obligates us to provide for them the
information of a gothic love that will
actualize that potential into personhood
now that there might be some other ways
in which you might still object you
might say well human beings are in the
image of God some people said that and I
I don't think that is fair to me I made
it clear that I'm not a Christian and so
simply asserting a doctrine to me is
unfair to me there's no there's there's
no shared normativity between you and I
if that's all that's happening I have no
way of responding to them if you're not
just asserting a doctrine but you are
making a metaphysical claim the
metaphysical claim might be something
like well human beings have souls and
animals do not I would would like to
first pause here and note that that has
that doctrine or at least that assertion
because I want to make a distinction I
should here between a doctrine an
assertion so I want to correct myself
that assertion right has not also been
morally innocent it has served as a
justification for a lot of cruelty and
in human inhumane action towards animals
so we have to be careful about that so
this notion of a soul is a very
problematic notion
and meaning and that overlaps with
another question that people have about
you know why my commitment to
physicalism and then that is usually
discussed in connection to the phenomena
of consciousness and the idea is that
there's something inherently no I'm
physical about us because we possess
consciousness and consciousness has
something inherently non-physical about
yet first of all as I stated in the
series I respect this I mean I think
this is a philosophically respectable
position so to say that I disagree with
it is not to say that I hold people who
hold that view and sort of intellectual
disrespect
now notice what's happened in the
history of this the things that we try
to claim were non-physical about us have
been shrinking if you go back a century
or so there was a there was a you know
the idea of vitalism was the claim that
there is something inherently
non-physical about being a living thing
so that living things had to use brooks
lamas famous phrase in a land battle
which sounds like an amazing hair
preparer hair shampoo elad patel this
vital spirit that was not captured by
any kind of physical description nobody
that i know are used for vitalism in any
more and if you take a look at the
polling even Americans in Americans one
of the most religious countries in the
world
there's just an ever-increasing number
of people who will admit or say that
they accept that life is a purely
biological phenomenon and so the idea
that you know that soil stuff was sort
of integral to life has been fading then
and of course there was the attempt to
sort of well there's something special
about intelligence that we are
especially intelligent and that points
again to something non-physical about us
as we've learned more and more about the
capacity of our nearest biological
cousins even dogs right but but let's
say bonobos and chimps the claim that
they don't possess a lot of what we call
our intelligence is becoming more more
untenable and of course also as
artificial general intelligence the
that looms ever more pressingly the
claim that there's something
non-physical about intelligence is
drifting away and so for example if you
look at a work of a theologian I respect
John Hicks um he when he's talking about
the relationship between neuroscience
and spirituality religion he does not
try to make an argument for a
non-physical aspect of human beings in
terms of life or intelligence he zero
zero on consciousness I am NOT going to
now in the next five minutes try to
solve the problem of consciousness that
is ridiculous and pretentious
what I want to say is why I think it is
why why I have the position I have on
consciousness and I will because what
I'm responding to here is the some
people have said well I'm just sort of
dogmatically toeing the scientific line
that you know it's just a dogma mmm I
don't think that's fair and that's what
I want to respond to here so I want to
make it clear that I'm not claiming to
give the knock down account of
consciousness or anything ridiculous
like that I'm really responding to the
claim that by Reiki is saying these
things because you know that's just what
the scientist has to say yeah so
famously trauma is distinguished between
the hard and the easy problems of
consciousness the easy the easy it's not
easy you just means it's doable the easy
problem of consciousness is trying to
explain what consciousness does I won't
repeat the arguments I made in this
series I gave a bunch of convergence
arguments that what consciousness seems
to be doing is a special higher-order
version of relevance realization so what
he means the hard problem is the nature
of consciousness how does something like
consciousness emerge out of things that
don't possess consciousness like
physical processes and that seems to
zero in on that what are called the
problem of qualia qualia are the
experiential centers of consciousness
it's the experience of blueness right
right and the idea is there's nothing in
the physics that gives us that that that
qualitative aspect of our experience
now I agreed that this is a very
problematic thing there's two things I
would say about this is that people tend
to lump together two different types of
qualia there's much you might call
adjectives a qualia like the blueness
when you're experiencing blue or that
that that felt nastiness of pain when
you're experiencing pain but there's
also adverbial qualia this has to do
with other with sort of that I that my
experience is perspective tilings have
aspects for any ways in which right that
they are relevant to me and things are
centered on me so that sort of there's a
phenomenological field there's a
prospective well I'm the subjective
center of that and that sort of
centeredness and hospitality and
temporality I'm going to come back to
this later in this series I'm going to
just just release argument I think that
can actually be explained in terms of
the functionality of relevance
realization that the ability to generate
a salience landscape and so forth will
account for those either real things so
that the the sticking point for claiming
the unknown physicality to consciousness
is are these qualitative right these
these adjectives of qualitative aspects
of our experience and and and and there
are good arguments and Chalmers has made
some and others that that we may not be
able to give a physical explanation of
them I'm not going to go over all these
arguments gonna give one argument just
as a demonstrative example the argument
goes something like this imagine two
people who have an inverted spectrum
what that means is whenever I'm
experiencing greenness in my subjective
experiencing they're experiencing
redness and whenever I'm experiencing
redness they're experiencing greenness
and the point about that is we will we
will function exactly the same we will
both point out an apple and say green
because I'm using the word green suppose
I'm privileged and green lines up with
green this and then the other person is
using the word green and it lines up
with their at their qualia for redness
the point is we will act and say
everything there'll be no causal
behavioral difference between us we will
act exactly the same but we will have
and qualia attached to our actions and
our experience and then arguments along
of this ilk are designed to show that
two things could be causally and
functionally identical and have
fundamentally different qualia and that
means that there will be no physicalist
explanation of qualia as I've said I
think this only applies to adjectives
Ollie are not a verbal qualia so let's
grant the possibility that adjectives of
qualia can not be given a physical
explanation this is a very Pyrrhic
victory because the that argument that
shows that qualia cannot be given a
physical explanation also shows that
qualia have no causal powers that they
have no determining difference making
capacity for your behavior
they cannot change your behavior and
this is part of the larger problem that
if the mind is in some way non-physical
it can't causally interact with the
undeniably physical nature of your body
and so what you end up having to say and
this is of course what some philosophers
find worrying is that these qualia which
are so central to the claim that
consciousness is non-physical are epi
phenomenal they have no causal role they
have no causal function
they can't affect your behavior etc so
that is as I say that's a very Pyrrhic
victory it seems to me the opposite is
true that it is the felt nastiness of
pain that is somehow affecting my
behavior my physical behavior I touch
the Fargo aisle and my hand moves back
that's a physical motion and so it seems
more plausible to me that qualia must
have some causal capacity and therefore
they should ultimately be capable of
being given a physical a physical
explanation now even if that's not the
case and I keep admitting there's many
people I respect who would say no no in
the end qualia are non-physical I'll
accept their epi phenomenal status right
I wonder of whether or not they are
the constitutive of consciousness so
many people have reported informant has
written books on this and I've
experienced myself that in a deep
meditative state you can get to a state
called the pure consciousness event
you're not conscious of anything
there's no you're not conscious of
yourself you're not conscious of redness
or anything like that
you're it's a pure consciousness event
so there are no adjectives of qualia in
your consciousness at all that's a
defining feature of it now what's
important is the adverbial qualia are
still there there's a hereness and a
noun and a unity to your experience so
the adverbial qualia don't throw away
the object type of qualia do and that is
I think just an incontrovertible
argument that magic Tavo qualia are not
necessary for consciousness that you can
have consciousness without them
and so again they're the arguments for
their existence random render them at
best a few phenomenal they do not seem
to be necessary for consciousness I
doubt that they're sufficient i if you
just had disconnected blips of redness
and blueness that were in no way bound
together prospectively and could make no
impact on your behavior would that be
consciousness it's very it's at least
questionable now all that being said I
have no illusions or delusions that I've
convinced many of you that is not been
my goal my goal has been to try to show
that there are there's arguments right I
think good arguments for the position
that I'm taking and then I'm not just
espousing the position I'm exposing
because it's you know it's Dogma and
we're not allowed to trespass on the
heresy or physicalism other that that
may be the case for some people but I'm
not under that kind of dogmatic
compulsion I am making the claims I'm
making for the reasons that I have
articulated to you so I tried to answer
sort of those two questions together
because although they're distinct
questions they overlap any mesh in
important ways there's another question
question or series of comments that I
want to address and then I'll get to the
tweeted ones and then I'll get hopefully
to some of the live ones this has to do
with some people saying to me things
along the phone lines that they
basically just sort of say well you know
why are you doing it's all just an
illusion meaning and you're but you know
and there's often a bit of a I don't
know what to call it I don't I don't
know these four people directly or
personally but there's there's a I
sometimes sense that there might be some
condescension in it right you know isn't
it obvious that nihilism is true and you
know people are just deleted to to talk
about meaning etc etc I want to respond
to that because I think that that
position is a little bit more difficult
than the people who espouse it realize
and the argument I mean I have to make
an argument that I'll make in much more
detail later I have to make it somewhat
schematically and quickly but the
argument goes something like this the
argument is that the the the the
determination of truth depends on
meaning if I'm going to determine if
something's true I have to be able to
first understand its meaning if I say to
you
Google Fripp's often bippy Bob is that
true or false you have no way of
answering that because you don't know
what I met and and the meaning of course
that I'm talking about if we think that
there's something to empiricism is of
course not just the meaning of
utterances it's that the meaning of my
statements right the propositional
meaning is somehow connected right to
the structural meaning in my experience
right the way I'm making sense of my
environment and so that if you sort of
say well I you know I don't either is
meaning and truth necessarily
presupposes meaning for its
establishment it's not quite clear what
you are now doing because you can't be
asserting a belief and to say you know
well there really aren't beliefs or we
right I don't know what that means you
know to believe something is to believe
that it's true of I believe acts if I
say I believe that cats are a mammal but
I think the proposition cats are mammals
are false that that's just that's just
inconsistent and so insofar as you're
committed to
asserting true beliefs you're committed
to the indispensability of meaning
now you may bite the bullet and you may
say you know maybe a form of a limit of
materialism you may say well I I
actually think that there are no such
thing as belief how that isn't self
contradictory is very difficult for me
but you know you may you may embrace a
kind of comprehensive skepticism you may
say yes I get that what I'm doing is
self undermining but I accept the self
undermining and what I'm actually saying
is it completely self undermines and
there's nothing and I embrace the kind
of absolute skepticism I accept that as
a possible position but then what you
have to I would argue what you have to
agree to is that that position is not
adopted on the basis of argumentation or
evidence precisely because you have
denied the possibility of argumentation
because you've denied belief and truth
and you rely if the possibility of
evidence which is also required because
evidence is defined as something that
changes beliefs because of its potential
truth etc so all of that being said what
that means is trying to assert that
there is no meaning is a very difficult
position to sustain now maybe you can
but simply asserting F or asserting it
as obvious or that's what we should
conclude I think is very problematic now
as our history led us to the prevalence
of nihilism very much and I acknowledge
that that's part of what the series is
saying but you might be saying as well
maybe there's meaning but the value of
it is it is a delusion again the value
of truth and the value of meaning are
bound up together and if you value truth
then of course it you are you're
required to value meaning and so again
saying that that's a delusion or
illusory illusion is is very hard to
maintain again
I am NOT trying to refute nihilism as a
physician I'm trying to refute the idea
that it is the obvious clear
indisputable conclusion we should just
simply accept you know that meaning
doesn't exist or that we shouldn't value
it I try to show why that is deeply
deeply problematic I'll try to in the in
this in the course of the series advance
other arguments as to both the
indispensability of meaning and a way I
think of understanding it that can fit
it back into our ontology and and by not
putting it so easily into our
established epistemological categories
of either subjectivity or objectivity
but that's that's an argument that I'll
have to just promise because it's it's
coming in the series so though that's a
lot of the heavy lifting and I wanted to
address those three questions because
many people were bringing them up in one
way or the other and I was trying to
show and you know I understand like you
know you can't make all the arguments
that you need to make when you're making
a statement and so I'm not taking this
opportunity to try and lay out some of
the arguments for some of the claims
I've made again trying to show you that
these there are there is reason behind
some of the claims I'm making that it's
not just you know a dogmatic adherence
to a scientific worldview or that you
know I swim with scientists so I have to
be quiet about certain things so now I'd
like to pass on to some of the questions
that were tweeted and then we'll shift
gears a little bit here because these
questions I think are and I don't this
is not meant to be in any way a
dismissive or demoting these questions
tend to be a little bit more practical
than orientation not quite so
philosophical and full-blown theoretical
us one question is how can one not be
autodidactic in a place where there is
no wisdom center so yeah and
I take this question very very seriously
I am I will remain critical of
autodidact ISM but the fact that for
many of us there are no wisdom centers
often means where we are thrust into
this that is precisely one of the
problematic aspects or dimensions of the
meaning crisis that we shouldn't be
autodidactic in the pursuit of wisdom
but we seem to be forced into it because
of a lack of you know traditions guides
and centers I don't have a good answer
to that other than to tell you what I'm
trying to do about it I mean so as I've
said before one of the gifts of these
theories as I get to and I'm
increasingly interacting with people who
are who are scenting setting up such
centers and such communities they're
there's real time and real talent being
put into creating these things and in a
very preliminary fashion and I've
started to talk to some of these people
I'm trying to get them to network
together and to join and to link up with
other networks we would like to create
something like a virtual wisdom
Institute where we create a co-op that
would help to vet these various groups
facilitate their development for
facilitate their coordination mutual
support and try and extend a network
that would help to address this concern
of giving people places where they can
reliably and safely go to start pursuing
wisdom and self transformation and a
less autodidactic fashion and so as I
said I'm trying what I can about that I
also plan to release although this
doesn't completely address the
autodidactic but hopefully to help some
instruction videos about you know
various practices that I refer to how
would you go about trying to learn in
this practice but hopefully the goal for
that is to not to reinforce people you
know staying in their homes are learning
but to get some preliminary skill
development so that they then have you
know the educated
sensibility to go out and find and
evaluate well various groups so I take
that concern seriously and I there's
things I'm trying to do and planning on
doing to try and address it the next one
is are you a sports fan it depends what
you mean by that I mean I enjoy playing
certain sports I enjoy playing soccer
played it a lot in high school and
things like that and you know tennis and
things like that I used to follow hockey
for a while but sort of fallen away from
that my life is just really incredibly
busy
I don't follow basketball and so I I
hope the Raptors win just because of my
allegiance to Toronto and things like
that so not that much of a sports fan I
am paradoxically I'm very interested in
sports psychology I'm very interested in
the psychology of sport and of coaching
because that has been very informative
for me try to understand
transformational experience and
perspective 'el and participatory
knowing so although I I'm not directly a
sports fan I enjoy going to a baseball
game or going to a hockey game I I'm
much more an enthusiast of sports
psychology so what's my daily routine or
habits I was interviewed about this and
I talked about it I'm not quite sure
what to say about that Mike my days my
days have some constants in them and
there but there's also parts that are
very different I usually begin the day I
have Meniere's disease as some of you
may know it's an unfortunate disorder
it's chronic and there's no known cure
and what will periodically happen is my
inner ear will fill up with fluid and
that will put tremendous pressure on my
inner ear and I'll get ringing in the
ear pain tremendous vertigo vomiting
it's it's I would not wish it on my
worst enemy or nemesis it
I'll take pain really really bad pain
over that experience so I'd start my day
with having to do a series of exercises
that are designed to try and moderate
and alleviate the veneers and then that
usually leads into a whole set of
practices I do I do
various forms of Tai Chi Chuan I do some
Chi cung I do some pranayama some yoga
and then I do sitted meditative practice
contemplative practice and then I do
some other Safian chill practices drawn
from the Neoplatonic tradition and then
I generally do some lectio divina I'm
not reading a Bible and I mean no insult
to Christianity although there's
evidence that lectio Divina is not
specifically of Christian origin so I
don't feel that that's inappropriate
there seems to be some evidence that it
goes back to a Neoplatonic heritage so I
will often do a lectio divina this is a
special kind of reading that I've
already talked about in in the series
and right I'll do that with some
Neoplatonic texts I'll do that with a
Taoist text and some Buddhist texts and
so I started today with a series of
practices that way and then my game
varies considerably sometimes I'm
teaching and other times I'm doing
research sometimes that research
involves discussing with other people
sometimes it involves you know looking
at the work that's done in my lab on the
some of the experiments we've done the
consciousness and wisdom Studies lab so
I have no I hope sorry that's very
strong statement right I hope I have no
delusions about how privileged I am
I mean I've worked very hard to get
where I am but I'm very lucky in that I
get to do work that I find very deeply
meaningful and to interact with
colleagues and students that you know
these are bright
fried enthusiastic interesting people
and so I I'm just extremely grateful for
that and I acknowledge that that leads
to another question so there is a
question about you know finding work
which alleviates or engages in
alleviating the meaning crisis are there
institutions or organizations that are
you know awful useful help for people
who want to develop wisdom or essential
psycho technologies there are again
that's part and again I'm not the expert
in this I'm learning about it because
I'm coming into contact with you know
groups of people who are setting things
I had a wonderful discussion with a
person from obscure plen this morning
and he does some really interesting work
he set up a charitable organization in
which he's teaching mindfulness to youth
at risk to prison inmates to adults
going and facing trauma and so and he
wanted to talk to me because he wants he
was considering ways about sort of
broadening that to to address the issues
around the meeting crisis because he
took he was making a case a case I agree
with by the way that a lot of the mental
health issue is is actually exacerbated
and perhaps in some sense derivative
from the mental health crisis is
exacerbated and derivative from the
other meaning crisis so there are there
are people who are setting up places
where they teach places where there is
an integration of teaching and therapy
there's a places where there's in
tradition of teaching therapy and and
community building and so III my hope
and and there's at least some
preliminary evidence for this is that
this will be a growing sector of the
economy I think some of the more
traditional sectors there's possible
avenues within teaching within therapy
there's obviously all kinds of important
work you know in which
doing care for people palliative care in
which all of this is important of course
you may want to go into the root help
facilitate some of the research on this
you know research that's going into
psychedelics altered states of
consciousness meaning in life so that
would be an academic thing so that is my
best answer right now I understand that
it's not that satisfying an answer and
like I said I'm hoping that this will
gel and grow as a part of a part of our
economy it will need to because
loneliness and meaninglessness are
growing we're facing the aging of our
population which tends to increase the
possibilities of meaninglessness and
loneliness and things like that the
society need heroes
is there something regular people can
trust inside or outside of ourselves
that helps them to avoid being lied to
mostly so-called saviors who take
advantage of the need for meaning so
there's a lot in that question that I
think is so the question is and this is
this is part of the you know the
distrust that has built up and and of
course the fact that we still hunger for
Heroes is easily evidenced by you know
the success of things like endgame the
Avengers movie and all the TV shows
around the Marvel Universe etc we talked
and we talked about that in the book
Chris and fell open on so it's a very
real concern that people take advantage
of our need so here's why I think we
need for lack of a better term heroes I
mean you know we need there's increasing
research you know you go to Grossman has
good research and I'll talk about this
later in this series the Solomon effect
that if you can move from disgust so you
have a very difficult problem has to do
with respective of knowing and when when
people typically describe
they describe it from the first-person
perspective if that person read ascribes
the problem from a third-person
perspective that often will help them to
have insight into the problem this lines
up with some it's convergent with
evidence from the Berlin paradigm
studying of wisdom that if when you're
trying to solve a wisdom task you
imagine talking to someone else that
will help you to to better solve the
problem and of course all those things
both line up with the fact that we we
improve our own metacognitive ability by
internalizing the perspective other
people have on us so Leo Ferraro
and I argued that one of the things that
seems to be across many different wisdom
traditions is the trains perspective on
knowing to bring about these
improvements in our capacity for insight
and solving the problems that are most
pertinent to us is a process of
internalizing this age we we have to
find figures who are wiser than us that
we can imitate and emulate the way a
child imitates an adult and that's
problematic I'll come back to this up
but analogous to that so that we can
develop these skills of reflective
metacognition that will improve the
cultivation of wisdom now of course that
is problematic because an adult child
relationship is not the kind of
relationship that should exist between
adults and that's where the sport
psychology has also been valuable
because the relationship between the
coach and the athlete is also an analogy
I would use you can see that the athlete
often has to go through this process of
internalizing the coach and what that
looks like and in order to you know to
translate you know the knowledge into
the perspective of knowing into the
procedural and purchase the procedural
skills and participatory transformation
of their of who they are in order to
become the kind of athlete they want to
become so that gives us another sort of
way of thinking about it and then
there's you know when it's done properly
there's a teacher-student relationship
so if we can try and
you know use many different models the
hope is that we could come up with a way
of finding these people in a beneficial
fashion Jensen Kim has one of my former
students and current colleagues has done
research within wisdom traditions and
many people have many instances of very
positive role models for their
cultivation of wisdom so that is a very
prevalent thing that all being said this
is precisely why we need what I was
mentioning earlier we need some co-op
non-hierarchical but co-opt organization
that's mutually self-correcting mutually
supporting for trying to vet
institutions and individuals in some
sort of way and also that you know a
curriculum a shared curriculum it could
be diverse it doesn't have to be a
monolithic but shown vetted shared
curriculum precisely to address the
possibility of you know you know abuse
and I think the degree to which
individuals can cultivate their skills
in the ways that I've suggested may help
with that process so someone a question
has here has advancements in machine
learning cars because any revision to
your thesis the naturalistic imperative
is unattainable
so that's literally my PhD thesis about
the naturalistic imperative and if
somebody went out and read that
congratulations you're that's really
that's very that's then that's that
shows a real commitment to trying to
understand something yes the answer to
that is yes and so my more recent
publications especially work that I've
done with him willow craft Blake
Richards
leo Ferraro and others have pointed to
the fact that these advancements I think
have changed my mind towards the
possibility of solving the naturalistic
imperative precisely because the work
that I've done
with one of you know like Tim is one of
the Tim level-cap is one of the you know
stars of you know the work on machine
learning and and both Tim and Blake were
two co-authors with me on the relevance
realization paper the point I'm trying
to make is that I think the the advances
in machine learning can give us some of
the theoretical tools for talking about
an explanation of relevance realization
that's now in publication in terms of
machine learning and I think and as I
argued in my thesis that was the problem
that was sort of resisting attaining a
satisfy a satisfactory account of the
naturalistic a satisfactory solution to
the naturalistic imperative so yes it
has definitely changed it and I invite
you to go out and seek some of those
publications and you can see how the
change works okay so I'm now going to
try and move to some of the live
questions I I'll do my best to get to
all of them but I apologize if I can't
once again for somebody like myself
who's very socially phobic and who finds
this kind of putting myself out there
for lack of a better phrase deeply
challenging huh very stressful for me
I'm sort of balding my ear right now in
fact I'm deeply appreciative of the fact
that and people of course welcome to
disagree with me I'm deeply appreciative
of fact that people are supportive
they're respectful and and they're
enthusiastic so again thank you thank
you very much so how did one cause of
one person was very interested in the
pure consciousness event how does the
body react to the pure consciousness
event is there a response depends what
you mean I mean I use a model upon to
turn the the lived body is not present
in the pure consciousness event because
because there's a there's a sense in
which I'm not present John Berbick II
completely disappears no before that
gets a goal no think about how much that
overlaps with phenomena that's not as
sort of strange which is the flow state
which I've talked about in the series
when people
in the flow state they regularly and
reliably report a loss of
self-consciousness so it is not
problematic and and notice what what and
this is this is something really really
crucial I think it's one of the
fundamental insights of Buddhism I'm not
promoting Buddhism here but we normally
have this idea that and that you know
that our ego and our agency are
identical that if I lose my ego that you
know that that self conscious eye that
self conscious a narrative Li
constructed identity I lose that at
least my agency and Buddhism is saying
no that's not necessarily the case and
what the flow phenomena I think shows is
that you can lose your ego precisely in
a way that enhances your agency because
the enhancement of your agency is
exactly what's happening in the flow
State now the the so your sense of you
know your the sense of being job right
disappears there that sense of having
even a first person sort of presence to
oneself
you're not even conscious of your
consciousness so in in that sense the
body is the lived body is not present to
you in awareness but I imagine and I
work needs to be done on this there's
another way that question could be
interpreted what's happening in your
brain and what's happening in your body
physiologically and neurologically
during the pure consciousness man I am
deeply interested in this question
I'm deeply interested in this question
and I would like to know better what
what what is going on I imagine there's
significant design deactivation Newburg
has in the book why why God won't go
away he has the hypothesis that the
areas of the brain what he calls the
orientation Association area the areas
of the brain that are sort of
responsible for locating you physically
in space are being deactivated during
these deep states of meditation and
therefore your sense of being anywhere
in particular is dissolving and you're
getting that
no awareness now that's not the same as
no here nowness which is really as I
emphasized earlier which is very
important and so I imagine there's huge
changes patterns of deactivation
shifting of processing we know that
psychedelic experiences get different
areas of the brain to talk so in that
sense I think there's major probably
unique responses happening
neurologically and physiologically
during the pure consciousness event it
seems to it seems like an episode 19 you
said that Augustine philosophy was
beautiful and maybe even complete does
this mean that we need to get back to
Augustine's philosophy in some way that
I I did think that Augustine's
philosophy was very beautiful in the way
that he integrated Christianity and
Latinas and the Aristotelian narrative
word of via the inquiry the
incorporation of Platonic because petha
Latinas had already integrated Aristotle
with with Plato so I do think it's very
powerful than that it's this really
beautiful admirable articulation of the
of the narrative and normative and
neurological orders and as I argued that
seems to line up very clearly with the
way people currently articulate as you
know scientifically the dimensions of
meaning in life the purpose the
narrative order coherence the normal
logical order and significance depth
right the normative order so in the
sense that we need to get a worldview
that can beautifully articulate the
three orders in a way that fits into the
agent arena relationship of our
worldview Andrea Ford's worldview
attunement then there's a sense in which
that is what we need to do but I do not
think we can return to Augustine I I
mean so the the series goes on to
show the history of how the Augustinian
view was significantly undermined and
that and and not just undermine
philosophically as I tried to show there
are the there are there is always the
creation of new psycho technologies it
was the invention of new set of
technologies that created the changes in
consciousness and cognition that you
know promoted the two worlds mythology
that you know came to a kind of fruition
in Augustine but there have been new
psycho technological developments since
then and just like we can't go back to
the Bronze Age before the actual
revolution because we cannot give up the
psycho technologies of literacy and
numeracy and abstract symbolic thought I
don't think we can go back to the
Augustinian worldview because we cannot
give up the psycho technologies that we
now have like graphing in the scientific
method etc etcetera the ones that I up
the ones that I lay out in this series
so in that sense I don't think we can we
should or can go back to Augustine I
think then I've tried to portray this I
think we should pay Augustine deep
respect and see what can we salvage from
that Augustinian view now I know that
Jonathan and pesho' and the Paul van der
clay will probably disagree with me on
that and and I'm happy to discuss that
with them so I'm just giving the reasons
for the answer that I have given what's
my favorite color I'm not sure I know I
don't really I don't really you know I I
tend to like a kind of soft blue a lot
of times I guess I don't know that
reveals anything about me but
interestingly enough so what on one of
my feelings about existential threats do
you think humanity will survive
[Music]
the coming century so I don't think I
should comment in things on things for
which I don't have expertise just
offering you my untutored and
unsubstantiated or uneducated opinions
it's something that I don't want to do I
do think that there is good evidence and
good reason for you know some very
serious looming threat psychological you
know socio-economic potentially
potentially military etc also there's a
potential that a I could go long in some
important ways and that I have a little
bit more expertise about and at some
point I'm going to talk about that and
the difference between artificial
intelligence and artificial rationality
in the series so the only area I feel
competent to address on is that I do
think that the meeting crisis
exacerbates and interferes with our
ability to respond to these other crises
I've made this argument before and so
I'll briefly review it the idea is in
order to answer these kinds of these
very significant existential threats I
think we have to bring about really
radical transformations and
consciousness cognition character
communitas and that's very problematic
for us because many of us are post
religious and we distrust as some of the
people in the lot of questions of
showing religious institutions because
of the history so we can't make use of
the thing that is in the past been
responsible for bringing about that kind
of comprehensive transformation in the
threat in the face of serious
environmental and/or historical change
and that's religion so for many of us
that's not available to us but we also
have significant distrust and the
secular alternatives political machinery
political ideological movement pseudo
religious ideological movements and we
distrust those of course because of
their history and it's the way
they drench the earth and Titanic blood
so I do think what I can say is that if
we do not come up with a significant
response to the meaning crisis I think
that's that
there is reason to believe that will
radically increase the probability that
we will succumb to one of these deep
threats and that is of course one of the
urgent motivating factors for why I'm
doing all of this and why so many people
and it is now so many people I'm aware
of me so many people are trying to bring
about the changes it of course is I
think a very sad state of affairs and I
I'm not taking a political side here I'm
making a meta political comment it is a
very sad state of affairs that the these
issues and the meaning crisis issue and
its attendant you know issues of mental
health and loneliness these are just not
central concerns in the political arena
and that that means that means I think
isn't it isn't it a plausible conclusion
that there is no political solution as
the police said that it's going to have
to be a cultural solution in some
powerful way and so that's the hope is
that what I see happening culturally
these groups in these movements will
well they've taken root they will grow
and flourish and I hope I can help that
one one sign of hope is people will good
evidence they will go through radical
transformation they will suffer radical
diminishment in their standard of living
and other things if they have good
confidence that their meaning in life
will be enhanced so that means we do
have a motivational engine if we can
if this becomes a culture and that's an
important if then it does have important
motivational purchase on people because
if people have good reason to believe
that they that sacrifices in standard of
living and etc would would would be
commensurate with you know increase in
wisdom and meaning people will there is
good reason to believe that people will
do that so that's the best I can say
about that question okay you talked
about poetry that has a contemplative
meditative aspect to it especially when
spoken aloud any recommendation fit this
criteria I think a lot of poetry does
and and III think I mean there's some
poetry that is just meant to be recited
you know I I'm a big fan of EE Cummings
you know with up so floating mini bells
down just saying that the musicality of
it is just a serious part of the poem
but I mean I find that the musicality of
poetry is I find it in in a lot of the
poetry that I read and it just and
that's what happened in that in that
poetry party it just comes out when it
is recited and shared but recitation
means you know said aloud in the company
of other people that are giving caring
attention to it I think a lot of poetry
would be improved by that one of the
things I'm going to do I'm in the
process of starting to do is just you
know collect a YouTube playlist of
poetry that I think is expressive and
reflective and responsive to the meeting
crisis and I will I will eventually make
that available and start adding to it on
an ongoing basis kind of analogously to
the way I do the book recommendations
the four on Twitter for people who are
interested in are responding to the
meeting Chris I have one more question
I'll try and make it a light everyone do
you like dancing so um that's that's uh
that's an interesting one so I'm a
highly socially full pic and so in
general I don't like dancing and I guess
this is also sort of generally a feature
of men we don't like dancing but that's
it really exacerbated for me social
phobia
now I do like I deeply like isn't the
right verb I deeply appreciate and savor
the dance like aspects of doing Tai Chi
Chuan for example or yoga and that leads
to a funny story my my partner she she
loves dancing and I've gone to a dance
with her and she's Persian and so there
was Persian dancing and it was like at
first oh no what am I gonna do is gonna
be terrifying but what I found was all I
had to do was sort of modify some Tai
Chi movements and postures and I was I
was able to come off as a passively good
Persian dancer so that was one of the
best dance experiences of dancing
experiences I've ever had in my life so
unfortunately we're running out of time
and and there's a lot of questions that
people have sent and and that are still
coming through I will try and gather
them together again and you know put
them you know you know take them forward
into the next give some of them I can't
give all of them I'm sorry you have some
of them pride of place when we come to
the next question and answer session I
will try to mention some of these if
possible when I'm being interviewed
going for four in the future I take
seriously my responsibility to try and
respond to your questions as extensively
as I possibly can ah and so
you can we you can post those questions
are with hashtag meeting crisis
oh and also hashtag ask for baking okay
so both of those so that's our time for
tonight and I you know and there's a lot
of people that are you know coming in
and say hi and shouting out and again I
I wish I could respond to that a lot of
people are thanking me for my time I
want to thank all of you and I always do
and I will need you to all believe that
it is always sincere I want to thank all
of you for your time and attention thank
you very much and I hope you all have a
good evening